University Of Connecticut
© 2005 University of Connecticut
University of Connecticut, Legal and Legislative Records.
1881-1982.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Center.
University of Connecticut.
1 linear foot.
MSS19980125
As Connecticut's state university and its land-grant college, the University of Connecticut's history has largely been shaped by its relationships with the state and federal governments. The present collection is intended to bring together the state and federal legislation and the judicial cases, which have defined those relationships, together with contemporary discussions of these matters.
History
As Connecticut's state university and its land-grant college, the University of Connecticut's history has largely been shaped by its relationships with the state and federal governments. The present collection is intended to bring together the state and federal legislation and the judicial cases, which have defined those relationships, together with contemporary discussions of these matters.
The records from the 1880s and 1890s reflect the young institution's struggle to establish itself in the first years after its founding in 1881. In 1886-1887, it had to withstand a legal challenge to the validity of the Storrs brothers' gift to the state of the land on which the school was built. As this dispute was being settled, controversy was already brewing over the disposition of the state's federal land grant. Powerful agricultural interests in the state were dissatisfied with the use of being made of the federal finds by Yale's Sheffield Scientific School, which had been designated as Connecticut's land-grant institution after the passage of the first Morrill Act of 1862, and sought to have the funds transferred to the Storrs School. The celebrated “Yale vs. Storrs” controversy was ultimately resolved by the passage of Public Act 67 of 1893, which established Storrs Agricultural College and opened the way for the subsequent transfer of the land grant to Storrs. Yale replied by bringing a suit against the state. When the courts failed to decide the case conclusively, a commission was created which awarded damages to Yale for the loss of the federal monies and, in effect, confirmed the status of the S.A.C. as Connecticut's land-grant college.
A succession of federal grants strengthened and broadened the mandates received by the state in the original land-grant legislation. The second Morrill Act of 1890 directed federal resources toward the “more complete endowment and support of the colleges for the benefit of agriculture and the mechanic arts” which were established under the act of 1862. Other legislation, such as the Smith-Lever Act of 1914, defined the work of the land-grant colleges in such areas as agricultural extension work. Summaries of this important legislation are contained in the publications “Federal Laws, Regulations, and Rulings Affecting Land-grant Colleges,” contained herein.
Having secured the claim to the federal grants, the college at Storrs still faced a protracted struggle to obtain adequate financial support from a recalcitrant state legislature. Records in this collection such as an essay by college trustee W. E. Simonds and the text of a legislative hearing in 1903 point up the difficulties experienced by Storrs Agricultural College and, from 1899, Connecticut Agricultural College, in its relations with the state during this formative period.
The passage of an act changing the name of Connecticut Agricultural College to Connecticut College in 1933 was a signal of the legislative support and public acceptance that the college had at last won by this time. Six years later the legislators voted to change its name again to the University of Connecticut, thus recognizing in law the growth achieved by the college during these years. The 1939 act represented the culmination of a long process, begun by the act of 1893, in which the small agricultural school became Connecticut's state university.
Revisions of the state's general statutes in 1945 and in 1958 have further defined the legal status, functions, and authority of the University and its officers and staff.
Scope and Content
This is an artificial collection assembled to illustrate various legal and legislative aspects of the history of the University of Connecticut. The individual items were acquired over many years from a number of sources. The collection is divided into four sections according to the type of record.
Arrangement
Series I: Connecticut Legislation ( 1881-1982 ) includes the acts establishing Storrs Agricultural School and Storrs Agricultural College, legislative proceedings and budget proposals, and contemporary discussions of the college's relations with the state government. Copies of the 1933 and 1939 acts changing the name of the college are also included here.
Series II: U.S. Legislation ( 1909-1925 ) consists of a number of bills and acts in the U.S. Congress which have affected land-grant colleges, and the federal publications “Federal laws, Regulations, and Ruling Affecting Land-grant colleges,” which include the texts of the Morrill Acts of 1862 and 1890.
Series III: Articles and Summaries ( 1883-1975 ) contains essays and reports concerned with the legal status of the college in its relations with both the state and federal governments. W. E. Simonds' 1893 publication, “Concerning Connecticut Agricultural College Funds,” for example, summarizes federal land-grant legislation up to that time and discusses the awarding of these funds to Storrs Agricultural College.
Series IV: Legal Cases ( 1886-1922 ) is made up of reports of the proceedings in the critical legal cases of the 1880s and 1890s, which ultimately secured the position of the institution as the state's land-grant college.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of records pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Organizations:
University of Connecticut—History.; Universities and colleges—Connecticut—Law and legislation.; State universities and colleges—United States—History.; Agricultural colleges—United States—History.; Education, Higher—Law and legislation—United States.; State universities and colleges—Connecticut—History.
Document Types:
Administrative Records.; Legal Class.
Occupations:
Institution of Higher Education
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Artificial collection created by University staff.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Connecticut Legislature, 1881-1982
  - Act establishing Storrs Agricultural School, 1881 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Act establishing Storrs Agricultural College, 1893 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Act changing the name of Storrs Agricultural College, 1899 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Legislative hearing on bills relating to appropriations for the Connecticut Agricultural College, 1903 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Connecticut Agriculture—a budget, 1911 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Act changing name to “Connecticut State College”, 1933 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Act changing name to “University of Connecticut”, 1939 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Some pertinent legislation regarding the University of Connecticut, 1941 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - 1945 Supplement to the General Statutes, “The University of Connecticut” (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - General statutes of Connecticut, Revision of 1958, (revised to 1964), “The University of Connecticut” (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Summary of legislation affecting the University, 1982 (Box 1:, Folder 36)
  - Vol. 1: Special Acts and Public Acts #39-367, 1975 (Box 2:, Folder 37)
  - Vol. 2: Public Acts #421-636, 1975 (Box 2:, Folder 38)
  - Public and Special Acts, 1976 (Box 2:, Folder 39)
  - Public and Special Acts, 1976 (Box 2:, Folder 40)
  - Legislation of interest to the University, 1974-1978 (Box 2:, Folder 41)
- Series II: U.S. Legislation, 1909-1925
  - H.R. 15422: Bill for increase of appropriation... for extension work, 1909 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Vocational Education Bill, 1911 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Smith-Lever Bill for Agricultural Extension, 1914 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - Department of the Interior, Federal Laws, Regulations, and rulings affecting the land-grant colleges of agriculture and mechanics arts, 1916 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Department of Agriculture, Federal Legislation, Regulations, and rulings affecting agricultural colleges and experiment stations, 1919
  - Department of Agriculture, Federal Legislation, Regulations, and rulings affecting land grant colleges and experiment stations, 1930
  - Purnell Bill, 1925 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - Legislation concerning agriculture: H.R. 11997, a bill creating federal cooperative marketing board, and S. 4158, a bill to prevent a recurrence of agricultural depression,., 1925 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
- Series III: Articles and Summaries, 1883-1975
  - Acts of the congress of the United States and of the Legislature of Connecticut pertaining to the National Grant of Public Lands for the promotion of Scientific Education, 1883 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Resolution of title to land, 1886, 1938 (Box 1:, Folder 36)
  - Olcott, J.B., The Storrs School vs. Sheffield Scientific School, 1887 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - The Agricultural Funds of Connecticut, 1890 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - Simonds, W.E., Concerning Connecticut Agricultural College funds, 1896 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
  - Simonds, W.E., Concerning funds for Storrs Agricultural College, 1899 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
  - U.S. Bureau of Education, General Laws (state and federal) Relating to Agricultural and Mechanical Land-Grant Colleges, 1905 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
  - Obligations of the State to the Federal Government in relation to the Connecticut Agricultural College, 1912 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
  - Relations between the United States Department of Agriculture and the Agricultural Colleges and Experiment Stations: Addresses by E. Davenport and B.T. Galloway, 1913 (Box 1:, Folder 24)
  - Federal and State Laws Affecting the Connecticut Agricultural College, 1925 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
  - Recent Laws Affecting the Connecticut Agricultural College, 1929 (Box 1:, Folder 26)
  - Hill, John, G., compilation of laws affecting the University of Connecticut, 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 27)
- Series IV: Legal Cases, 1886-1922
  - Storrs Agricultural School vs. Whitney, 1886 (Box 1:, Folder 28)
  - Storrs Agricultural School vs. Whitney, 1887 (Box 1:, Folder 29)
  - Storrs Agricultural School vs. Whitney, in The Atlantic Reporter, 8:2, 1887 March (Box 1:, Folder 30)
  - Yale University vs. The State of Connecticut: Argument of Counsel for the State, 1893 (Box 1:, Folder 31)
  - Yale University vs. The State of Connecticut: Brief for Respondent...on Immunity of State from Private Suit, 1893 (Box 1:, Folder 32)
  - Yale University vs. The State of Connecticut: Brief in support of the claim submitted to the Commissioners by “The Corporation of Yale University, 1893 (Box 1:, Folder 33)
  - Yale University vs. The State of Connecticut: Public acts And Other Documents, relating to the Controversy between the Corporation of Yale College and the State of Connecticut, 1893 (Box 1:, Folder 34)
  - U.S. Supreme Court, Massachusetts vs. Mellon: Brief on behalf of the Association of Land Grant Colleges, 1922 (Box 1:, Folder 35)